Guide to the Time Inc. New Building Department Records 1953-1967 MS 3009-RG 16
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. New Building Department Records
1953-1967
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 16
5 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
The New Building Department Records contain the decisionmaking and planning files for the construction of Time Inc.'s new office space, the Time & Life Building, which is part of Rockefeller Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library. The Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3) have files about the creation of and move to Time & Life Building and other files about Time Inc. offices.
Scope and Contents Note
The New Building Department Records contain the decisionmaking and planning files for the construction of Time Inc.'s new office space, the Time & Life Building, which is part of Rockefeller Center. Series I contains the chronological binders kept by the head of the department Henry "Hank" Luce III. Series II contains other materials created by the department during the planning period. Series III contains invoices and purchase orders for construction, interior decor, and furniture.
Historical Note
In December 1956 Time Inc. announced plans to construct a new Time & Life Building in cooperation with Rockefeller Center, Inc. located at 1271 Avenue of the Americas. Harrison, Abramovitz, & Harris were the architects. Around 1954 Time Inc. created the New Building Department, headed by Henry "Hank" Luce III and assisted by vice president Allen Grover, to oversee the project. This department may have developed from the Publisher's Subcommittee on Housing.
Arrangement Note
Organized into three series:
Series I. Henry Luce III Chronological Binders
Series II. Subject Files
Series III. Invoices and Purchase Orders
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include privileged attorney correspondence; student records; medical records; personnel performance evaluations; contracts and agreements; and records with personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in box R7. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporations -- History.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Harrison, Abramovitz, & Harris; Luce, Henry, III, 1925-2005; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- Buildings; Time, inc. -- History; Time, inc. -- Management; Rockefeller Center -- Buildings
- Series I: Henry Luce III Chronological Binders, 1956-1960; 0.75 Linear feet in 1 record carton
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Henry Luce III Chronological Binders appear to be kept by the head of the department as a record of the sequence of events. Luce is the primary author with a substantial amount of material from department staff member Alex Hood included. The files contain memoranda, correspondence, cost estimates, and Publisher's Subcommittee on Housing meeting agenda and notes. Of interest is a July 1958 survey of the editorial reference material undertaken to determine space requirements.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized chronologically.
  - Chronological Binders, 1956-1960 (Offsite-box 712, Folder 1-14)
- Series II: Subject Files: New York Offices, 1953-1967; 2.5 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
  The Subject Files appear to have been processed and organized by the Time Inc. Archives and look similar to files found in the Time Inc. Subject Files and the Time Inc. Annex Files.
  The first folder contains ideas for possible sites while the rest of the folders focus on the construction and set up of the Time & Life Building. The files contain planning records such as memoranda, correspondence, cost estimates, publicity clips, and meeting minutes for various committees and groups including the subcontractors and Publisher's Subcommittee on Housing. Also included are plans for a building cornerstone and the time capsule placed within, financial information with regards to purchasing furniture, and references for design choices. Records indicate that several large decisions were made jointly by Time Inc. general manager and vice president Roy Larsen and Rockefeller Center board member Nelson Rockefeller. One item of interest includes a ceremonial trowel for the cornerstone laying.
  Organized alphabetically.
  - New Sites, 1953-1955 (Offsite-box 712, Folder 15)
  - Time-Life: Designs for Business, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 712, Folder 16)
  - Time-Life: Designs for Business: Legal [RESTRICTED], 1957-1960 (Offsite-box R7)
  - Time-Life: Elevators, 1956 (Offsite-box 712, Folder 17)
  - Time-Life: Fuller-Lowry: Legal [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R7)
  - Time-Life: Financial: Furniture, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 712, Folder 18)
  - Time-Life: Financial: Miscellaneous, 1954-1957 (Offsite-box 712, Folder 19-20)
  - Time-Life: Financial: Miscellaneous, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 1-2)
  - Time-Life: Financial: Profit and loss summary, 1956 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 3)
  - Time-Life: Fuller-Lowry subcontractor's meetings, 1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 4)
  - Time-Life: Heliport Proposals, 1956-1957 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 5)
  - Time-Life: Miscellaneous, 1956-1962 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 6)
  - Time-Life: Move: Miscellaneous, 1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 7)
  - Time-Life: Move: Miscellaneous [RESTRICTED], 1959 (Offsite-box R7)
  - Time-Life: Move: Time Incers, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 8)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Advertiser Relations, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 9)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Coordinating Committee, 1956-1957 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 10)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Cornerstone, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 11-12)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Design Committee, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 13-14)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Design and Sketches (Brennan), circa 1956 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 15)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move-Directors Memos [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R7)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Furniture Meetings, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 16)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Job Meetings, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 17-18)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Miscellaneous, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 19)
  - Time-Life: Publicity: Clips, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 713, Folder 20)
  - Time-Life: Publicity: Miscellaneous, 1956-1965 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 1-3)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Publisher's Subcommittee on Housing, 1955-1958 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 4)
  - Time-Life: Pre-Move: Rock-Time Meetings, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 5-6)
  - Time-Life: Special Areas: Dining Rooms: Hemisphere Club, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 7-8)
  - Time-Life: Special Areas: Dining Rooms: Miscellaneous, 1956-1966 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 9)
  - Time-Life: Special Areas: Library, 1956-1960 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 10-11)
  - Time-Life: Special Areas: Miscellaneous, 1956-1967 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 12)
  - Time-Life: Special Areas: Plaza, 1960-1967 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 13)
  - Time-Life: Special Areas: Reception Center, 1959-1967 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 14-15)
  - Time-Life: Sublet Space, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 16)
- Series III. Invoices and Purchase Orders, 1959-1961; 1.25 Linear feet in 2 record carton
  Invoices and Purchase Orders consists of material removed from three binders. DFB Purchase Orders and Untitled contain purchase orders and invoices for furniture, interior decor, and plants. Subcontractors' K & Co Amounts includes invoices for "Time Inc. Tenant Work" regarding construction. All binders contain a small amount of correspondence to and from Time Inc. regarding work to be done and credits on returns.
  - Untitled Binder, 1960 (Offsite-box 714, Folder 17-19)
  - DFB Purchase Orders, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 3817, Folder 1-10)
  - Subcontractors' K & Co Amounts Binder, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 3817, Folder 11-15)